Hedgehogs are not a particularly
powerful, fast, or flexible species. In
fact, compared to many others in their
environment, they're fairly slow [music]
and weak. But, hedgehogs successfully
survive using one effective strategy.
They curl into a ball, expose their
spines, and become difficult to attack.
On the opposite end of the spectrum,
foxes are a nimble, fast, and adaptable
species. For both hunting and defense,
they employ a variety of strategies,
like hiding, pouncing, scavenging,
running, as well as acclimating to
various environmental conditions.
Neither the foxes nor the hedgehog's
strategy is universally right or wrong,
better or worse. Both species have and
continue to survive. But, there's
something very interesting about the
differences between them. As the ancient
Greek poet Archilochus said, "The fox
knows many things, but the hedgehog
knows one big thing."
There are several interpretations one
could make of this line, but 20th
century philosopher Isaiah Berlin used
it as a metaphor to define and contrast
the two primary ways in which thinkers,
writers, and public figures, which we
can extend to people more broadly,
approach ideas.
In his essay, The Hedgehog and the Fox,
Berlin argued that one common category
of thinkers, which he referred to as
hedgehogs, view and treat the world
through clear, definable frameworks.
These individuals are often very
confident about their scopes of
understanding [music]
and conclusions. Berlin writes, "They
relate everything to a single central
vision, a single universal organizing
principle, in terms of which alone all
that they are and say has significance."
Berlin contrasts hedgehogs with another
category of thinkers, which he referred
to as foxes, who, on the contrary, view
and treat the world as something more
nuanced, [music] malleable, and
uncertain. These individuals are far
less likely to reduce phenomena into
singular domains or theories, and are
also less likely to be highly confident
[music] in their conclusions.
Like a fox, they're willing to adapt,
either pounce or hide, depending on
context. Berlin writes,
"They pursue many ends, often unrelated
and even contradictory, connected if at
all only in some de facto way for some
psychological or physiological cause
related to no moral or aesthetic
principle."
The invasive species of the modern
world.
A lot has changed since Berlin's essay
in 1953. The quantity and impact of
thinkers and public figures expressing
ideas, theories, advice, and so-called
facts hasn't merely increased, but
proliferated in modern culture.
Now, anyone can publish and share
essentially anything online at any time
with access to the entire world. We
encounter the thoughts and views of
hundreds, if not thousands, of ordinary
people, experts, crackpots, interesting
thinkers, good-faith communicators,
bad-faith communicators, charlatans,
artists, marketers, or some combinations
thereof on a daily basis.
On one hand, this is remarkable. We have
constant access to some of the best and
most interesting minds on the planet,
and we can engage with others' minds
through all sorts of efficient and
interesting mediums. We have access to
their insights, theories, protocols,
advice, and modes of thought on a
real-time basis, some of which can be
extremely interesting, useful, or even
life-changing for both individuals and
society at large.
But on the other hand, we also have
equal access to mediocre, deficient, or
malicious minds who share just as many
thoughts and views, often with far more
conviction and noise.
And it can sometimes be hard to tell
them apart. As a result of both our
psychology and the ways media platforms
exploit our psychology, we are very bad
at parsing and focusing on good
information
>> [music]
>> and good-faith communicators.
We are more attracted to, and media
platforms primarily amplify, confidence,
charisma, contrarianism, resonance,
fear-mongering, simplicity, certainty,
and so on.
None of which on their own are markers
of high-quality information or
good-faith communication. In fact,
they're often indicators of the
opposite.
The Expert Economy.
Most of us strive to see and understand
the world as clearly and simply as
possible. [music] We yearn for clear
answers and explanations because deep
down we know, or perhaps feel, that life
and reality [music]
are devoid of them.
In our stubborn need for existential
orientation, we attempt to map words and
concepts onto the world trying to create
a perfect overlay between thought and
reality.
But this is like taking a literal
physical map as the equivalent for the
territory it symbolizes.
The map is very useful, but it is also
very incomplete. It cannot show all the
objects, people, [music] dimensions,
weather, or events existing and shifting
in each moment within the territory.
And you cannot traverse the map itself.
We all feel the unsettling dissonance
between our perception of reality and
the limited control and understanding we
have of it. We have our maps, but they
don't show us why or how we should go
anywhere [music]
and what will happen if we do.
What's actually around the corner?
As a response to this, instead of
acknowledging and embracing the
dissonant ambiguity inherent to
existence, we often strive for clearer
maps, origins to blame our circumstances
on, clear routes to escape our
circumstances, clear destinations to
hope for.
As a result, [music] there is a massive
ever-expanding economy built not so much
around the actual clarity of maps, but
the marketing and saleability of the
clarity of maps.
This is because as a species, we really
can't understand things much more
clearly. That is, we can't
comprehensively understand or predict
much about reality, the variability and
complexity of people's lives, economies,
societies, the metaphysical
underpinnings of it all, and so on.
But we can continue to sustain and sell
the hopeful illusion that we can.
Foxes are more often right, but you know
of way more hedgehogs.
Building on the work of Isaiah Berlin,
American political psychologist and
author Philip Tetlock spent nearly two
decades studying 284 experts, including
academics, journalists, analysts, and
public intellectuals. Almost all the
participants in the study had
postgraduate education, were publicly
recognized, and on average [music]
had roughly 12 years of work experience
in their field. Tetlock and his team
collected and tracked 28,000 of their
predictions about the world across 18
years, measuring both the accuracy of
their predictions and their levels of
confidence in them.
In the end, [music] across the board,
the experts' predictions were barely
better than chance.
Even the most accurate cluster of
experts performed only slightly better
than simple mindless predictive models.
Crucially, however, there was a spectrum
of different thinking styles and
confidence levels exhibited by the
experts, ranging from those who are
narrow and confident to those who are
more open and tentative.
Here, Tetlock borrows the fox and
hedgehog terms from Berlin to define the
two primary groups he found in his
analysis. Hedgehogs being more confident
and likely to extend their views into
many domains, and foxes being more open
and tentative.
Interestingly, Tetlock found there was a
clear group that was significantly more
accurate in their predictions and
self-assessments.
Foxes.
In other words, the group of experts
that were the most confident were the
least accurate. In fact, they were worse
than chance. Tetlock writes, "Treating
the regional forecasting studies as a
decathlon between rival strategies of
making sense of the world, the foxes
consistently edge out the hedgehogs, but
enjoy their most decisive victories in
long-term exercises inside their domains
of expertise."
Speaking of overconfidence around
information and predictions, [music] one
of the noisiest and messiest arenas for
this is the mainstream news. This
video's sponsor, Ground News, is a
platform that provides solutions for
these very problems: information
overload, misinformation, media bias,
and manipulation. It works by gathering
news from all around the world and
organizing it into one spot. You can
then compare the headlines, framings,
political leanings, and corporate
ownership of all the news sources
reporting on the same stories, allowing
you to cut through the noise and
manipulation and differentiate facts
from politics [music] and
sensationalism. For example, with SpaceX
recently completing the largest IPO in
history, there's a lot of different
sources reporting on the event, both
analyzing and predicting its
implications, [music] from the stock
market to the future of technology and
humanity. Using Ground News, I can
immediately see that only 18% of the
sources reporting on the story are
left-leaning. [music]
So, if you're someone who primarily gets
your news from left-leaning sources, you
could have missed coverage of it
altogether.
>> [music]
>> With Ground News, I can also see how
different outlets are framing the event
based on their headlines and biases. In
this case, left-leaning sources are
being more cautionary and skeptical
about SpaceX's valuation, while
right-leaning sources tend to frame it
as a positive economic triumph.
And to help solve your own personal
blind spots, Ground News also has a
dedicated blind spot tab, which
specifically curates news stories that
you wouldn't otherwise likely encounter,
so you can identify and correct your own
biases [music]
and narrowness.
Ground News's mission and platform fully
embody the kind of intellectual humility
and transparency [music]
this world so desperately needs. Get a
clearer understanding of what's actually
going on in the world by going to
ground.news/pursuit
or by using my QR code, and you'll get
40% off their unlimited [music] access
Vantage Plan.
The secrets to success.
Ironically, what we tend to reward and
be attracted to in media and popular
discourse is precisely what makes the
ideas within them more likely to be
fallible. The shows, podcasts, books,
and content that confidently claim clear
answers to life, clear resolutions to
problems, clear origins of suffering,
clear predictions or assessments of
what's happening or likely to happen,
are more likely to be weaker compared to
those who explore ideas with openness,
ambiguity, and hesitancy. [music]
Tetlock writes,
"The net result is a double irony, a
perversely inverse relationship between
prime exhibit indicators of good
judgment and the qualities the media
prizes in pundits,
>> [music]
>> the tenacity required to prevail in
ideological combat, and the quality
science prizes in scientists, the
tenacity required to reduce superficial
complexity to underlying simplicity."
Perhaps this still might seem
counterintuitive. Individuals with
shows, books, podcasts, lots of
experience, lots of money, social
status, [music] big audiences, or all
the above, must know more than the
average person, must have greater
talents or intellects, [music] must be
keen to more secrets and insights, must
be special. Maybe, maybe not. It
depends, and it depends on a lot.
And that's the problem.
Firstly, when it comes to personal,
self-help, or success-oriented advice,
and this should be fairly obvious, what
works for some people doesn't mean it
will work for everyone. In some cases,
it won't work [music] for most, if not
all others.
Each person is an entirely unique blend
of biological [music]
and psychological makeups, combined with
a unique set of environmental, social,
[music] and economic circumstances, all
stirred together through an entirely
unique sequence of experiences.
No one will ever have the same unique
concoction of existence
>> [music]
>> as anyone else throughout the entire
universe in perpetuity.
Each of us alone walk the path of our
feet and occupy the space of our heads
in every moment. [music]
Besides the profound and somewhat
unsettling existential implications of
this,
>> [music]
>> it is also inexorable within this that
each of us will develop unique skills,
abilities, and perspectives, or lack
thereof. That includes everything from
athleticism to articulacy [music]
to wittiness to thinking styles to
self-discipline,
and everything else.
Academic and neuroscientist Robert
Sapolsky writes,
"You cannot decide [music] all the
sensory stimuli in your environment,
your hormone levels this morning,
whether something traumatic happened
[music] to you in the past, the
socioeconomic status of your parents,
your fetal environment, your genes,
whether your ancestors were farmers or
herders. [music]
Let me state this most broadly. We are
nothing more or less than the cumulative
biological and environmental luck over
which we had no control that has brought
[music] us to any moment.
Furthermore, as a result of who and
where we are, we will each uniquely
encounter or not
>> [music]
>> information, resources, and
opportunities at various points within
our lifetimes. Even if two people
inherently possess the same [music]
skills or abilities, but one starts off
with certain economic or social
advantages, or they happen to have some
serendipitous good fortune in their life
at an opportune time, this person is
almost certainly going to achieve
greater levels of success.
>> [music]
>> And if one argues that their ability to
encounter opportunities or accumulate
resources was a product of their
ambition or self-discipline, [music]
where then did these propensities for
ambition or self-discipline come from?
Ultimately, any simple universalized
prescription for how to live or become
successful [music]
are in direct opposition with reality.
The one thing we can know.
Referring back to Tetlock's study,
though the hedgehog experts were wrong
more significantly and more often than
[music] the foxes, the foxes were still
wrong a lot. They were not much stronger
at assessing the world than simple
mindless extrapolation [music] models.
And although they were far less extreme
in the degree of their confidence, their
confidence levels were still mostly
higher than their abilities.
The conclusion here is, ironically,
clear. Although there is a better, more
robust way of thinking and assessing the
world, with sufficient time or
complexity, we rarely know what we are
talking about. We are dramatically worse
at understanding and forecasting the
world than our feelings of confidence
[music] imply.
It's very hard to embrace nuance and
ambiguity. It's harder to convey and
express it. And it's hardest of all to
package and sell it.
But that is what this world really is.
Messy, convoluted, ambiguous, [music]
and contradictory.
One theory will not resolve the cosmos.
One daily routine or mindset will not
resolve a life.
It's mostly luck, but it's not
pointless.
In the end, sharing one's insights and
assessments, or making observations and
predictions, whether by experts,
writers, thinkers, or simply those who
care, is of course not bad or devoid of
value. In many cases, there's a lot of
value in it. Firstly, it's genuinely
interesting to engage in and hear out
different people's perspectives, ideas,
and insights, simply for its own sake.
And it is all the more interesting and
stimulating when it is from individuals
who have domain expertise, have had
success in life, or simply very
articulate or interesting in their ways
of thinking.
Secondly, there's of course nothing
wrong with sharing and seeking
knowledge, predictions, or advice,
regardless of category or expertise.
This is a natural tendency of humankind.
And in many cases, when done in earnest,
it is a noble and beautiful exchange
that points at the heart of our desire
to connect and persist [music]
through insight and wisdom.
Thirdly, there are of course real
experts and real domains that have real
knowledge or advantages. And when
information or advice is shared in good
faith by an expert about their domain,
for those for whom encountering said
information would benefit, it will.
And lastly, there's of course nothing
wrong with being confident, charismatic,
clear, or resonant. These qualities
certainly do not automatically imply bad
faith or bad information. And there's
broadly nothing wrong with being like a
hedgehog. Even within uncertainty, it
can be valuable to push ideas to their
limits in order to find their limits, in
order to make bold claims
>> [music]
>> or inspire bold change, in order to help
orient social or personal directions and
narratives.
Interestingly, one could say there is
something hedgehog-like in reducing the
complexity of cognitive styles into two
binary [music] categories: hedgehogs and
foxes.
And yet, it does gesture at something
important nonetheless.
The ultimate point is this.
When we are viewing, reading, or
engaging with people and ideas, it's
important to remember how easily
influenced we are by these factors
alone, and how little these factors
alone may indicate accuracy or merit.
Ultimately, success in life is not
expertise over life. Expertise in
certain domains is not expertise in
other domains, and neither expertise nor
success
>> [music]
>> ever equate to anything close to
clairvoyance.
Nothing grants anyone the ability to
grasp the ungraspable and know the
unknowable, which at enough distance in
time and space, and enough depth of
complexity,
everything is.
And so, those who say things like, "This
is the secret." or "These 12 steps will
transform X." or "This is why this
happened." and "This is what will
[music] happen." are perhaps the
hedgehogs of this world with their
spines out, using their one strategy to
avoid being attacked.
And to the contrary, those who say
things like, "Perhaps." or "It depends."
or "You might consider." or "This is
what worked for me."
are much more likely to be closer to
something real, [music]
true, or honest.
Maybe.
Maybe not.